نحن اليوم معكم من قرية الباسوطة، بريف مدينة عفرين الجنوبي.
We are with you today from the village of Basouta, in the
southern countryside of Afrin city.
لنحكي عن موسم الرمان، بعد ما حكينا في حلقة سابقة عن موسم
الزيتون بمنطقة عفرين.
To talk about the pomegranate season, after we talked in a
previous episode about the olive season in the Afrin region.
طبعا الباسوطة معروفة بأنها بلد الرمان، ووحدة من جنات سوريا
الطبيعية اللي الله خلق فيها كل الجمال اللي ممكن نشوفه
بالكون.
Of course, Basouta is known as the town of pomegranates, and
it is one of Syria's natural paradises where God created all
the beauty that can be seen in the universe.
الرمان في الباسوطة كتير مشهور، وفي كل سوريا، ومشهورين أهل
الباسوطة بصناعة دبس الرمان.
Pomegranates in Basouta are very famous, and in all of
Syria, and the people of Basouta are famous for making
pomegranate molasses.
اليوم رح نتعرف على الرمان وموسم الرمان وأنواع الرمان وكيفية
صناعة دبس الرمان في الباسوطة.
Today we will learn about pomegranates, the pomegranate
season, the types of pomegranates, and how pomegranate
molasses is made in Basouta.
ويمكن الأكلات المشهورة اللي بيتم استخدام فيها الرمان ودبس
الرمان. تابعونا.
And perhaps the famous dishes in which pomegranates and
pomegranate molasses are used. Follow us.
السلام عليكم. وين رايح؟ خلينا نحكي معك شوي.
Peace be upon you. Where are you going? Let's talk with you
a bit.
شرف لهون.
Come over here.
عربيتي ضعيفة ها.
My Arabic is weak, you know.
عربيتك ضعيفة؟ معلش. شلونك؟
Your Arabic is weak? No problem. How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
ع البركة، الله يعطيك العافية.
Blessings, may God give you health.
خلينا نروح عند الرمان، تفضل.
Let's go to the pomegranates, please.
عم بدي احكي بالكردي، بتعرفها؟
I want to speak in Kurdish, do you know it?
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
سلام ورحمة الله. أهلا وسهلا على راسي والله.
Peace and God's mercy. Welcome, my pleasure.
مرحبا يا شب. عم تاكل رمان؟ شلونك؟
Hello, young man. Are you eating a pomegranate? How are you?
طيب خلينا نوقف أنا هون، تفضل.
Alright, let me stand here, go ahead.
نحنا هذا شو بتسموا هذا الكوم الرمان هي؟
What do you call this pile of pomegranates here?
هاي كوم الرمان صابور اسمه.
This pile of pomegranates is called a "Sabour".
صابور؟ من التصبير؟
Sabour? From preserving?
من التصبير ايوه.
From preserving, yes.
يعني حفظ الرمان في جو بارد.
Meaning storing pomegranates in a cold environment.
ايوه.
Yes.
شلون بتصبروه؟ شلون بتحفظوه؟
How do you preserve them? How do you store them?
عم نحوش من البستان، عم نجيب لهون. اللي خربان عم نعزله.
We pick them from the orchard and bring them here. We sort
out the spoiled ones.
بنصفه على جنب نطالعه. بنعزله عن بعض، وكويس نحطه نصبره لهون.
We put them aside and take them out. We separate them, and
we put the good ones here to preserve them.
ايه بس يعني شلون بتصبروه؟ شو بتحطوله؟
Yes, but how exactly do you preserve them? What do you put
on them?
قش.
Straw.
تحته ولا فوقه؟
Underneath or on top?
تحته، ايه فوقه.
Underneath, actually on top.
وتحته؟
And underneath?
ما بنحط له شي.
We don't put anything.
إذا تحته ما بتحطوا له شي.
So you don't put anything underneath.
ما بنحط له شي، بأرض ناشفة نحطها.
We don't put anything, we put them on dry ground.
طيب ما بكون تحته رطوبة؟
Well, wouldn't there be moisture underneath?
ما في، بأرض ناشفة نحطها. إذا فيها رطوبة ما بنحطها.
There isn't, we put them on dry ground. If there's moisture,
we don't put them there.
ايوه، وفوقه قش. شقد سماكة القش؟
I see, and straw on top. How thick is the straw?
يعني شي ست سبع سمات يعني.
About six or seven centimeters.
خلينا نشوف هون. شرف معي.
Let's see here. Come with me.
سميك، من فوق انت كمان شوف سماكته.
It's thick, you can see its thickness from the top too.
تمام.
Alright.
ايه، يعني بتحط إيدك ما بيجي على المسطرة.
Yes, meaning if you put your hand, it doesn't touch the
ground directly.
والنايلو هادا؟
And this plastic cover?
النايلو مشان إذا نزلت مطر نغطي فيها مشان ما تنزل مطر فيها.
The plastic cover is for when it rains, we cover it so rain
doesn't get inside.
شقد بيبقى الرمان هيك؟
How long do the pomegranates stay like this?
شهر، أقل، أكثر، حسب السوق.
A month, less, more, depending on the market.
حسب السوق.
Depending on the market.
طيب بس طالعتوه من الصابور، إيش بتسووا فيه بعدين؟
Okay, but once you take them out of the "Sabour", what do
you do with them next?
ما في شيء بعدها، بننزله على السوق شلون، بننزله على السوق
بنبيعه.
Nothing after that, we take them to the market, we take them
to the market and sell them.
يعني إنتوا بتصبروه هون مشان يكون صار له سعر أحسن؟
So you preserve them here so they can get a better price
later?
ايوه ايوه، مزبوط.
Yes, yes, exactly.
شو نوع هادا الرمان؟
What type of pomegranate is this?
لفان.
Laffan.
لفان؟ ايوه.
Laffan? I see.
في الباسوطة هون إيش هي أنواع الرمان اللي بتنزرع؟
Here in Basouta, what types of pomegranates are grown?
في فرنسي وعصفوري ولفان.
There's French, Asfouri, and Laffan.
الفرق بيناتهم إيش هو؟
What is the difference between them?
عصفوري فيه حب ناعم.
Asfouri has fine seeds.
يعني حلو؟
Meaning it's sweet?
حلو، هاد لفان، لفان عم يعطي حموضة وعلى حلو.
Sweet, this one is Laffan, Laffan gives a sweet and sour
taste.
العصفوري بيجي حلو؟ بحلو يعني؟
The Asfouri is sweet? It comes sweet?
هو العصفوري هو الفرنسي مو هيك؟
Is the Asfouri the same as the French, right?
لا، فرنسي اسمه عصفوري فرنسي لحاله. فرنسي غير، اللفان وغير
العصفوري.
No, the French is called French Asfouri by itself. French is
different from Laffan and different from Asfouri.
الفرنسي لحال، اللفان، عصفوري، فرنسي، لفان كل شيء لحال.
French is on its own, Laffan, Asfouri, French, Laffan, each
is separate.
طيب إذا قلنا رمان سوري؟ الرمان السوري هاد هي الأنواع نفسها
الثلاثة؟
Okay, what if we say Syrian pomegranate? Are these three the
same as the Syrian pomegranate?
نفس السوري ايه، منطقة الباسوطة، شغل الباسوطة.
Yes, the same as the Syrian, from the Basouta region, grown
in Basouta.
في رمان أسود قال، شو هادا الرمان الأسود؟
There is a black pomegranate they say, what is this black
pomegranate?
هاد اسمه، مو شغل عنا هي.
That one, it's not grown here by us.
شغل وين؟
Grown where?
من ناحية بادية، لوين شو اسمه، بوكمال؟ أبو كمال، بيجي جلده
أسود.
From the Badia region, towards what's it called, Bukamal?
Abu Kamal, its skin is black.
لشو يستعمل هداك؟
What is that one used for?
نفسه، للدبس الرمان ولا للتصدير لبرا.
The same, for pomegranate molasses or for export abroad.
نفس الرمان، بس يجي جلده أسود هاد.
It's the same pomegranate, but its skin is black.
هلا إنت من هون؟ من الباسوطة؟
Now, are you from here? From Basouta?
من قبتان الجبل.
From Qabtan al-Jabal.
أهلا وسهلا. شو عم تساوي هون؟
Welcome. What are you doing here?
على راسي. جاي مشان أشتري وأبيع وأشتغل يعني.
Thank you. I came to buy, sell, and work.
اشتريت؟
Did you buy?
ايه ما بده يصير قسمة ان شاء الله عم نشتري.
Yes, whatever is destined, God willing, we are buying.
وين عم بتبيع؟
Where are you selling?
عم ببيع ع الطريق، بسطة ع الطريق.
I am selling on the road, a stall on the road.
شقد اليوم سعر الرمان؟
How much is the price of pomegranates today?
الرمان حسب، بـ 6، بـ 5، بـ 4، بـ 7، حسب.
Pomegranates depend, for 6, 5, 4, 7, it depends.
في معك بـ 10، في أكتر، في أقل، يعني حسب نظافة الرمان.
You have them for 10, more or less, meaning it depends on
the quality of the pomegranates.
سوق الرمان إيمت بيبدأ؟ يعني صباحاً في سوق للرمان؟
When does the pomegranate market start? Meaning, is there a
pomegranate market in the morning?
في مكان بينباع فيه الرمان بيتجمع فيه؟ ولا إنتوا بتروحوا ع
البساتين؟
Is there a place where pomegranates are sold and gathered?
Or do you go to the orchards?
لا طبعاً هلق في أسواق، في سوق الهال عفرين، في سوق الباب، في
سوق إعزاز، في سوق جرابلس.
No, of course, there are markets now. There's the Al-Hal
market in Afrin, the Al-Bab market, Azaz market, Jarabulus
market.
بس ما في سوق مثلاً بالباسوطة باعتبارها إنه بلد الرمان.
But there is no market in Basouta, for instance, considering
it's the town of pomegranates?
لا، ما في سوق. ما في غير بسطات ع الطريق. بسطات ع الطريق يعني
ما في.
No, there is no market. There are only stalls on the road.
Stalls on the road, meaning there isn't one.
شقد اليوم سعر الرمان للمبيع يعني؟
How much is the selling price of pomegranates today?
بالجملة يعني؟ بالجملة حسب، هلق مثل هاد، هاد رائين، هادك
رائين هادا حبة وحدة.
Wholesale, you mean? Wholesale depends, now like this one,
this is double-layered, that one is double-layered, this one
is a single piece.
مثل هاد يعني سعره بالـ 5. مثل هاد سعره بالـ 10، بالـ 9، 10.
Like this one, its price is around 5. Like this one, its
price is around 10, 9 or 10.
شلون ما فهمت يعني؟
How is that, I don't understand?
يعني هاد نوع أول، هاد نوع أول ليكه، هادا حبة وحدة، عرفت علي؟
Meaning this is first class, this is first class right here,
this is a single piece, you know?
هادا نوع تاني.
This is second class.
حبتين؟
Two pieces?
لكا، هادا نوع تاني.
Exactly, this is second class.
العاطلة منكبها لبرا، مفروز يعني شي متعوب عليه، هادا ناعم،
هادا للدبس.
We throw the bad ones out, it's sorted, meaning it's well-
worked on. This is small, this is for molasses.
خلينا نشوف الأخ اللي وراك. يعطيك العافية.
Let's see the brother behind you. May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health too.
هلا أنا قتلك تبتسم قلتلي والله ماني مبتسم بس تعبان.
Now, I told you to smile, and you told me, "I swear I'm not
smiling, I'm just tired."
الله يعطيك العافية، من ايمت جيت؟
May God give you health, since when have you been here?
تقريباً من العشرة.
Approximately since ten.
من العشرة الصبح؟ هلق عندكم كم شجرة رمان؟
Since ten in the morning? Now, how many pomegranate trees do
you have?
والله تقريباً شي 400 شجرة.
Well, approximately 400 trees.
ما شاء الله، هادا هو إنتاج السنة ولا بعتوا شي منه؟
Mashallah. Is this the production for the whole year, or
have you sold some of it?
لا هادا تقريباً كل إنتاج السنة، كل إنتاج السنة.
No, this is approximately the whole year's production, all
of the year's production.
السنة كان الإنتاج كويس؟
Was the production good this year?
والله ما بالنسبة للجو ما كان كويس.
Honestly, regarding the weather, it wasn't good.
ليش؟ خلينا نمشي شوي.
Why? Let's walk a bit.
بتعرف الجو كان بارد، والصقعة أثرت على الشجر ما حملت على
السوى.
You know the weather was cold, and the frost affected the
trees, they didn't bear fruit properly.
ايوه، يعني كان الإنتاج قليل؟
I see, so the production was low?
الإنتاج قليل.
The production is low.
بكل الباسوطة هيك؟
Is it like this in all of Basouta?
كل المنطقة، مو بس الباسوطة.
The whole region, not just Basouta.
هلا بالمنطقة هون، بمنطقة عفرين، مين أشهر بلد في زراعة
الرمان؟
Now in the region here, in the Afrin region, which is the
most famous town for growing pomegranates?
والله هي باسوطة معروفة.
Well, Basouta is known.
معروف رمان الباسوطة، إذا حكينا عن رمان الباسوطة يعني إيش شو
ميزاته؟
The Basouta pomegranate is famous. If we talk about the
Basouta pomegranate, what are its special features?
ميزاته ايش بدي أقلك، باسوطة هي فيها مي كتيرة.
Its features, what can I tell you, Basouta has a lot of
water.
والرمان بيحب المي كتير، لهيك نوعيته بتكون كويسة، كخشانة،
كلون، كنوعية يعني كل شي بتكون.
And pomegranates love water a lot, that's why its quality is
good, in terms of size, color, quality, everything is good.
طعمة ونكهة؟
Taste and flavor?
طعمة ونكهة، يعني كل شي بيختلف عن باقي الرمان.
Taste and flavor, I mean everything is different from other
pomegranates.
كم نهر في بالباسوطة؟ أنا بعرف في نهرين.
How many rivers are there in Basouta? I know there are two
rivers.
في نهر واحد بس في نبعة.
There is only one river, but there is a spring.
نبعة، نبعة ونهر؟
A spring, a spring and a river?
ايوه.
Yes.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
هي طريقة الفنية لتقشير الرمان؟
Is this the artistic way to peel a pomegranate?
نعم؟
Yes?
إله تقشيرة طريقة يعني؟
Meaning there's a specific way to peel it?
إله تقشيرة طريقة يعني، عرفت علي؟
It has a specific peeling method, you know?
إيش عم تعطيني إياه حرام. يا سلام، يا سلام. يعطيك العافية.
What are you giving me, it's a shame. Oh wow, oh wow. May
God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health too.
الكاميرا خلي تشوفها، مساها لإلك.
Let the camera see it, it's yours.
كويسة؟ لا لا ما هي كويسة، بس كان أبيض معناته جواته أبيض، هي
عاطلة.
Is it good? No, no, it's not good, if it was white it means
the inside is white, this one is bad.
بس هادا نوع كويسة.
But this type is good.
خلينا ننتقل لعنده والله، عندك ميزان. الله يعطيك العافية.
Let's move over to him, you have a scale. May God give you
health.
الله يعافيك. ان شاء الله ألف صحة.
May God give you health too. Hopefully a thousand healths.
أهلا وسهلا بالشباب نورتونا. الله يعطيكم العافية، فعلاً حلو
لفان.
Welcome to the guys, you lit us up. May God give you health,
indeed the Laffan is sweet.
شو عم تتسوق انت بالسنة؟ شو عم تتسوق كمية؟
How much do you market a year? How much quantity do you
market?
حسب، يعني هلق أنا بتضمن. هلق شجر ع الشجر ما ضل رمان تمام؟
It depends, meaning right now I rent the orchards. Now there
are no pomegranates left on the trees, right?
حوشت نزلت ع السوق بعت. وبضل أشتغل بلحق البراد، محل رمان
موجود بالبراد، أو الصابور.
I harvested, took them to the market, and sold them. And I
keep working, going after the cold storage, wherever there
are pomegranates in cold storage, or the "Sabour".
أنت بتتضمن من الأراضي كمان؟
You rent orchards as well?
بتضمن أراضي.
I rent orchards.
كاملة.
Completely.
ايه بتضمن، وبعد ما تخلص الأراضي بتاخد بقى بتصير تشتري من
الأسواق.
Yes, I rent, and after the orchards are done, you start
buying from the markets.
بشتري من الصابور، ايه، أنا هلق بشتغل هلق عالمفرق.
I buy from the "Sabour", yes, I am working retail right now.
بالضمان بنزل ع السوق ببيع جملة، عرفت علي؟
With the rented orchards, I go down to the market and sell
wholesale, you know?
هلق بصير لي صابور سبع تمن طونات، بشتغل لي فيهم كل نهار 500
كيلو 400 كيلو.
Now I get a "Sabour" of seven or eight tons, I work with
them, every day 500 kilos, 400 kilos.
ببيعهم مفرق ع الشارع، هيك يعني.
I sell them retail on the street, like that.
بس الضمان، بتضمن لي بالشي...
But the renting, you rent for...
Arabic: ...طنا ملي 50 طن 100 طن على حسب الاستطاعة يعني عرفت
علي شلون؟ ايه.
English Translation: ...a ton, 50 tons, 100 tons depending
on the capacity, you know what I mean? Yeah.
Arabic: الله يرزقكم
English Translation: May God bless you with provision.
Arabic: هيدي خيمة؟
English Translation: May God keep you safe.
English Translation: Is this a tent?
Arabic: هيدي الخيمة للحارس، خيمة مشان حرس الرمان هون
English Translation: This tent is for the guard, a tent for
guarding the pomegranates here.
Arabic: الله يرزقكم ويعطيكم العافية. يطرح البركة يا رب.
English Translation: May God bless you with provision and
give you health. May He bring blessing to it.
Arabic: السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Amen.
English Translation: Peace be upon you.
Arabic: سلام. على راسي والله.
English Translation: Peace. You are very welcome.
Arabic: السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Peace be upon you.
Arabic: وعليكم السلام.
English Translation: And upon you be peace.
Arabic: خيو انتو باركين بركة حلوة كتير وقدامكم المي، ليش ما
عم تصوركم؟ ما بتصوروا ضيوف؟
English Translation: Brother, you are sitting in a very nice
spot with the water in front of you. Why shouldn't I film
you? Don't you film guests?
Arabic: بس تصوير بقى.
English Translation: Just filming, then.
Arabic: والله معي الكاميرا بقى. طيب خليني اسلم عالشباب.
English Translation: Well, I have the camera with me.
Alright, let me greet the guys.
Arabic: اهلا وسهلا، مرحبا شلونك؟
English Translation: Welcome. Hello, how are you?
Arabic: خلي ابرك معك هون جنبك طالما انت... الله يعطيكم
العافية.
English Translation: Let me sit with you here, next to you,
since you... May God give you health.
Arabic: الله يعافيك اهلا وسهلا.
English Translation: May God give you health, welcome.
Arabic: بركتكم كتير حلوة، قدامكم النهر، الساقية، الله
يكرمكم.
English Translation: Your seating spot is very nice, you
have the river, the stream right in front of you, may God
honor you.
Arabic: شلون موسم الرمان هالسنة؟
English Translation: How is the pomegranate season this
year?
Arabic: والله كويس. مليح.
English Translation: It's good, honestly. Fine.
Arabic: شلون كويس يعني؟
English Translation: How is it good, I mean?
Arabic: يعني في بعض البساتين ضربهم الصقيع بس الموسم كان مليح
يعني الحمد لله.
English Translation: Well, some orchards were hit by frost,
but the season was good overall, thank God.
Arabic: عم تشتغل في الرمان انت؟
English Translation: Are you working with pomegranates?
Arabic: شو بتشتغل؟
English Translation: Yes.
English Translation: What do you do?
Arabic: والله انا كل سنة عندي ورشة لعصر بعمل دبس رمان.
English Translation: Honestly, every year I have a pressing
workshop where I make pomegranate molasses.
Arabic: هون؟
English Translation: Here?
Arabic: هون بالباصوطة.
English Translation: Here in Basuta.
Arabic: وين هلا الورشة؟
English Translation: Where is the workshop now?
Arabic: خلصنا صرنا اسبوع.
English Translation: We finished a week ago.
Arabic: كمان ودنا نشوفكم عم تشتغلوا.
English Translation: We also wanted to see you working.
Arabic: والله صرنا اسبوع مخلصين لانه ما ضل رمان هلا انتهى
يعني اخر موسمه.
English Translation: We finished a week ago because there
are no more pomegranates left now, it's over, at the end of
its season.
Arabic: بس بنلاقي حدا عم يعصر هلا؟
English Translation: But can we find anyone pressing now?
Arabic: ايه بيلتقى ما بيخلى بس بقى الشغل النظامي والكويس
خلصت العالم، اللي عنده ورشة كبيرة خلص.
English Translation: Yes, you can find some, it's not
completely empty, but the regular, proper work is done,
people have finished. Those with large workshops are done.
Arabic: شو الرمان اللي بتساووا منه الدبس؟
English Translation: What kind of pomegranates do you use to
make the molasses?
Arabic: والله من هالرمان الموجود، فرنسي، ولفان، هذا رمان
موجود هون يعني.
English Translation: From the available pomegranates here:
French, Laffan... these are the pomegranates available here.
Arabic: شقد اليوم سعره؟
English Translation: How much is its price today?
Arabic: الرمان؟
English Translation: The pomegranates?
Arabic: لا الدبس.
English Translation: No, the molasses.
Arabic: والله الدبس يعني من 65 ل 75 ليرة تركية عم ينباع
اليوم.
English Translation: The molasses is selling for about 65 to
75 Turkish Liras today.
Arabic: هذا النظامي الاصلي؟
English Translation: Is this the regular, original one?
Arabic: النظامي الاصلي ايه.
English Translation: Yes, the regular, original one.
Arabic: بينباع هون ولا بتصدروه لبرا؟
English Translation: Is it sold here or do you export it
abroad?
Arabic: هون وفي تجار بتاخد من هون هي بتصدر.
English Translation: Here, and there are merchants who buy
from here and they export it.
Arabic: لوين؟
English Translation: To where?
Arabic: والله لوين ما بعرف بس بياخدوا ناس ع النظام ناس على
تركيا ناس على دول الخليج واكثره بيطلع من هون ع النظام على
دول الخليج.
English Translation: Honestly, I don't know where to
exactly, but some take it to the regime areas, some to
Turkey, some to the Gulf countries. But mostly it goes from
here to the regime areas and to the Gulf countries.
Arabic: عملية عصر الرمان وتحويله لدبس، مربحة؟
English Translation: Is the process of pressing pomegranates
and turning them into molasses profitable?
Arabic: والله هاليوم ما ضل شي مربح.
English Translation: Well, these days nothing is profitable
anymore.
Arabic: ليش؟
English Translation: Why?
Arabic: يعني عبارة عن الواحد بس كونه يعني معيشة اول باول ايه
والحمد لله يعني مرابح ما ضل خالص.
English Translation: It's just a way for someone to make a
day-to-day living, yes, thank God, but there are no pure
profits left.
Arabic: طيب اللي بيعصر الرمان اربح ولا صاحب الشجرة اربح؟
English Translation: So, is the person who presses the
pomegranates making more profit, or the owner of the tree?
Arabic: لا طبعا صاحب الشجرة، انا عم اشتري الرمان الكيلو
احيانا بناخذه هذا للعصير بسموه قطاعة، كليته بليرتين ونص
بثلاث ليرات، السنة القطاعة من ليرتين ونص للثلاثة.
English Translation: The owner of the tree, of course. I buy
the pomegranates per kilo... sometimes we take it for juice,
they call it "Qata'a", its kilo is for two and a half to
three liras. This year, "Qata'a" is between two and a half
to three.
Arabic: كم كيلو رمان لحتى يصير عندك كيلو دبس؟
English Translation: How many kilos of pomegranates do you
need to get one kilo of molasses?
Arabic: والله السنة معدله 17 كيلو رمان، كيلو دبس. 17 كيلو.
English Translation: Well, this year the average is 17 kilos
of pomegranates for a kilo of molasses. 17 kilos.
Arabic: لانه الطن 70 كيلو، 65 كيلو 70 كيلو، هيك عمل معنا.
English Translation: Because a ton makes 70 kilos... 65 to
70 kilos, that's how it worked out for us.
Arabic: على النار؟
English Translation: Over the fire?
Arabic: طبعا ع النار وع الحطب.
English Translation: Of course, over the fire and wood.
Arabic: كم ساعة؟
English Translation: How many hours?
Arabic: من 8 ساعات لل 10 ساعات بياكل.
English Translation: It takes from 8 to 10 hours.
Arabic: هلا عندك دبس رمان هون؟
English Translation: Do you have pomegranate molasses here
right now?
Arabic: مو هون عندي والله بالبيت، انا هون زيارة عند ولاد
عمي، البيت فوق بالباصوطة.
English Translation: Not here, I have it at home. I'm here
visiting my cousins, the house is up in Basuta.
Arabic: الله يعطيكم العافية. الله يرزقكم، شكرا الكم يا شباب
الله يعطيكم العافية.
English Translation: May God give you health. May God bless
you with provision. Thank you, guys, may God give you
health.
Arabic: الباصوطة متل ما قلت قرية من اجمل القرى في منطقة
عفرين، السبب غناها بالمياه، نهر عفرين بيمر فيها
English Translation: Basuta, as I mentioned, is one of the
most beautiful villages in the Afrin region. The reason is
its abundance of water; the Afrin River passes through it.
Arabic: وايضا هناك نبع الباصوطة المعروف كتير لكل اهالي حلب
اللي كان عبارة عن مصيف،
English Translation: And there is also the Basuta spring,
which is very well known to all the people of Aleppo, as it
used to be a summer resort,
Arabic: نبع الباصوطة والمطعم اللي قربه، وايضا قرية الباصوطة
الغنية كتير بالفواكه المختلفة والثمار المختلفة وخاصة الرمان.
English Translation: the Basuta spring and the restaurant
near it. Also, the village of Basuta is very rich in various
fruits and crops, especially pomegranates.
Arabic: الرمان متل ما نحن شايفين الان، على يميننا وعلى
يسارنا اشجار الرمان. نحن اليوم في نهاية موسم الرمان،
English Translation: Pomegranates, as we can see now, on our
right and on our left are pomegranate trees. Today we are at
the end of the pomegranate season,
Arabic: متل ما قلنا في المقدمة، نحن في النهاية، نحن في
الاسبوع الاول من شهر تشرين الثاني.
English Translation: as we said in the introduction, we are
at the end, we are in the first week of November.
Arabic: موسم الرمان بيكون بالعادي في بداية الشهر العاشر
وبينتهي بنهايته. ولكن...
English Translation: The pomegranate season normally starts
at the beginning of the tenth month (October) and ends by
its close. But...
Arabic: السنة تأخر شوي بسبب ظروف الطقس.
English Translation: This year it was delayed a bit due to
weather conditions.
Arabic: لاحظوا الانواع المختلفة من الفواكه اللي موجودة في
هالقرية الحلوة.
English Translation: Notice the different types of fruits
available in this lovely village.
Arabic: معظم الاراضي مروية.
English Translation: Most of the lands are irrigated.
Arabic: طبعا القرية مبنية او موجودة على سفح الغربي الجنوبي
لجبل ليلون او جبل الاحلام المعروف.
English Translation: Of course, the village is built or
located on the southwestern slope of Mount Laylun, or the
well-known Mount of Dreams.
Arabic: فصل الخريف واضحة اثاره على اوراق الشجر المختلفة.
English Translation: The effects of the autumn season are
clearly visible on the various tree leaves.
Arabic: جمال الطبيعة، جمال رباني.
English Translation: The beauty of nature, a divine beauty.
Arabic: الناس هون بسيطين. ببساطة وجمال الطبيعة.
English Translation: The people here are simple. With the
simplicity and beauty of nature.
Arabic: اشجار الجوز على اليمين والسرو على اليسار.
English Translation: Walnut trees on the right and cypress
trees on the left.
Arabic: ايضا الزيتون.
English Translation: Also olives.
Arabic: ايضا نحن اليوم في موسم الزيتون.
English Translation: We are also currently in the olive
season.
Arabic: في تداخل بين البساتين والبيوت.
English Translation: There is an overlap between the
orchards and the houses.
Arabic: الان انتهت البساتين تقريبا ورح ندخل الان للقرية.
English Translation: Now the orchards have almost ended, and
we are about to enter the village.
Arabic: السلام عليكم.
English Translation: Peace be upon you.
Arabic: رح نزور معكم اهم معلم من معالم الباصوطة، واللي هو
نبع الباصوطة،
English Translation: We will visit with you the most
important landmark of Basuta, which is the Basuta spring,
Arabic: متل ما انكم شايفين، النبع هون، والنبع الاساسي هون،
English Translation: as you can see, the spring is here, and
the main spring is right here,
Arabic: وهذا مطعم ومنتزه الباصوطة الشهير اللي يعتبر مصيف
ومنتجع ومتنفس لاهالي حلب بالعموم.
English Translation: and this is the famous Basuta
restaurant and park, which is considered a summer resort, a
retreat, and a breathing space for the people of Aleppo in
general.
Arabic: المياه صافية، ومن هون بتنبع المياه، وبتسقي ايضا جزء
كبير من بساتين الباصوطة اللي بتنزرع بالفواكه والخضار
المختلفة ومنها الرمان.
English Translation: The water is clear, and from here the
water springs forth, and it also irrigates a large part of
the Basuta orchards that are planted with various fruits and
vegetables, including pomegranates.
Arabic: شاهدوا معنا كيف مية النبعة متجهة الان لازقة وشوارع
القرية وبساتينها.
English Translation: Watch with us how the spring's water is
now heading towards the alleys, streets, and orchards of the
village.
Arabic: هيدي المياه بتمشي في اقنية بعضها مكشوف وبعضها مغلق
او مسكر
English Translation: This water flows in channels, some of
which are open and others are closed or covered,
Arabic: وبشوارع القرية، وبتسقي البساتين لتصب اخيرا في نهر
عفرين،
English Translation: and through the streets of the village,
irrigating the orchards, to finally flow into the Afrin
River,
Arabic: وبتسقي باقي الاراضي من هون حتى توصل لعند الغزاوية
ولعند تل سلور ولباقي المناطق.
English Translation: and it irrigates the rest of the lands
from here until it reaches Ghazawiya, Tel Salour, and the
other areas.
Arabic: مياه صافية ونقية كتير واي حدا بده يروح ويرجع على
عفرين لازم يمر لهون
English Translation: Very clear and pure water, and anyone
who wants to go back and forth to Afrin has to pass through
here,
Arabic: ولازم يشرب ويغسل ويبرد متل ما بيقولوا وبعدين ممكن
يتغدى في المطعم ويتابع سفره.
English Translation: and must drink, wash up, and cool down,
as they say, and then they can have lunch at the restaurant
and continue their journey.
Arabic: تابعونا كمان نحن بجولتنا.
English Translation: Keep following us on our tour as well.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
شلونك؟
How are you?
(غير مسموع)
(inaudible)
مرحبا.
Hello.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
ما شاء الله، هذا بيدر الرمان؟
Mashallah, is this the pomegranate gathering place?
إيه.
Yes.
نتعرف عليكي؟
Can we get to know you?
ما بدها تحكي.
She doesn't want to talk.
طيب، أبو إدريس، معلش، أبو إدريس أنت مختار الباسوطة.
Alright, Abu Idris, it's fine, Abu Idris, you are the
Mukhtar of Basouta.
إيه، الله يعافيك.
Yes, may God give you health.
الله يعافيك. هلق عم نحكي على الكاميرا، احكي لي هلق هون شو عم
بصير؟
May God give you health. We are talking on camera now, tell
me what is happening here?
هلق هذول جايبين الرمان وعم يطالعوا الحب من الرمان وبعدين
بيعصروه، وهالمي هي بحطوها على النار وبيطبخوها وبتصير دبس
رمان.
Now they have brought the pomegranates, and they are taking
the seeds out of the pomegranates, and then they squeeze
them, and this juice is put on the fire and cooked to become
pomegranate molasses.
تمام. شو نوع الرمان هذا؟
Great. What kind of pomegranate is this?
مشكل، هذا رمان لفان ومشكل، يعني جايبين المضروب أكثر، هذا
الرمان اللي بقيان بالشجر جايبينه، يعني ما هو مستوي على
المزبوط كمان يعني.
It's mixed, this is Laffan pomegranate and mixed, meaning
they bring the more damaged ones, this is the pomegranate
that was left on the trees, meaning it's not fully ripe
either.
ليش؟ ليش ما بيجيبوا الرمان اللي نوعيته كويسة؟
Why? Why don't they bring the good quality pomegranates?
خلص يا أستاذ خلص الموسم.
It's over sir, the season is over.
طيب، قبل ما أطلع من هون، قبل ما نروح نشوف شلون عم يطبخوه،
هاي المرحلة اللي عم يساويها الشب الآن شو هي؟
Okay, before I leave here, before we go see how they cook
it, what is this stage that the young man is doing right
now?
هاي عصر الحب.
This is the squeezing of the seeds.
عم يعصروا الحب، بيطالعوا المي، بيصفوا المي، وبعدين بحطوها
على النار.
They are squeezing the seeds, getting the juice out,
filtering the juice, and then putting it on the fire.
هلق هذا الحب بقلب النايلون؟
Now, these seeds are inside the nylon bag?
إيه، هالحب هذا بيشيلوه بيحطوه بالكيس، وبيعصروه هيك، بيطلع
المي بيصفي لحال، والحب بيصفي لحال.
Yes, they take these seeds and put them in the bag, and they
squeeze it like this, the juice comes out and separates on
its own, and the seeds separate on their own.
أيوا، مرحلة وحدة بس العصر؟
Ah, is the squeezing just one stage?
إيه بس مرحلة وحدة.
Yes, just one stage.
يعني مرة وحدة بيكبسوه بس بيضغطوه؟
Meaning they press it just once?
بالضبط إيه.
Exactly, yes.
وبعدين؟
And then?
بعدين بيحطوا هالمي هي بيصفوه بمصفاية، وبيحطوه على النار
وبيطبخوه بيصير دبس رمان.
Then they put this juice, filter it with a strainer, put it
on the fire, cook it, and it becomes pomegranate molasses.
طيب خلينا نشوف هلق.
Well, let's see now.
شرف معي.
Come with me.
هاي الحلة للطبخ؟
Is this pot for cooking?
إيه للطبخ إيه. هلق منزلينها.
Yes, for cooking. They just took it down.
بس ضوي على الكاميرا بس، مشان نشوف. خلينا نجي لهون.
Just shine the light on the camera, so we can see. Let's
come over here.
هون هيدي، هيدي كأنه نحاس؟
Here, this, is this copper?
إيه نحاس، تبع الطبخ بيصنعوه من النحاس.
Yes, copper, the cooking pot is made of copper.
وهيدا هون بيشغلوا على الحطب.
And here they use firewood.
بالضبط إيه بيسحبوه بيشعلوا نار كذا.
Exactly, yes, they pull it and light a fire and such.
وهذا دبس الرمان.
And this is the pomegranate molasses.
إيه دبس الرمان جاهز، هلق منزلينه من فوق النار.
Yes, the pomegranate molasses is ready, they just took it
off the fire.
شقد بيحتاج يعني عصير الرمان على النار لحتى ينغلى لحتى يصير
دبس رمان؟
How long does the pomegranate juice need to boil on the fire
to become pomegranate molasses?
والله بده سبع ثمان ساعات لحتى يستوي.
Well, it needs seven to eight hours to be ready.
سبع ثمان ساعات؟
Seven to eight hours?
إيه بحيث يصير يعني سميك.
Yes, until it becomes thick.
بالضبط. تمام، هلق هذا رمان؟
Exactly. Okay, now is this pomegranate?
إيه هذول الشجر رمان.
Yes, these are pomegranate trees.
شو نوعه هذا الرمان؟
What kind of pomegranate is this?
أكثريته رمان لفان عنا.
Most of it is Laffan pomegranate here.
رمان لفان هذا كله؟ هذا بيصير منه الدبس.
All of this is Laffan pomegranate? This is what molasses is
made from.
دبس طبعاً دبس.
Molasses, of course, molasses.
هلق هون الناس بتسوي دبس رمان، مثل هدول الجماعة عم يساووا دبس
رمان، تجارة ولا هو من بستانهم؟
Now people here make pomegranate molasses, like these folks
are making pomegranate molasses, is it for trade or is it
from their orchard?
لا لا هدول في ناس بيجيبوهم من بساتينهم، وفي ناس بيجوا
بيشتروه من سوق الهال وبيجوا بيطبخوه.
No, no, some people bring it from their orchards, and some
people buy it from the wholesale market and come cook it.
طيب الناس هدول شو وضعهم؟
Well, what's the situation of these people?
لا هدول جايبينه من سوق الهال، عم يتاجروا فيه.
No, they brought it from the wholesale market, they are
trading it.
يعني جماعة بيتعيشوا منه؟
So they make a living from it?
بيتعيشوا منه أكيد إيه، بيستفيدوا منه شوي.
They definitely make a living from it, yes, they benefit
from it a little.
تمام. احكي لي عن تاريخ الرمان بالباسوطة.
Great. Tell me about the history of pomegranates in Basouta.
تاريخ الرمان، يعني من زمان أنا اللي بعرفه تقريبا من 100 سنة
أهل باصوطة بيشتغلوا بالرمان.
The history of pomegranates, I mean, for a long time, as far
as I know, for about 100 years, the people of Basouta have
been working with pomegranates.
يعني أول ما إجا الرمان على منطقة عفرين، أهل باصوطة اشتغلوا
بشغلة الرمان وزرعوا شجرة الرمان.
I mean, when pomegranates first came to the Afrin region,
the people of Basouta worked with pomegranates and planted
pomegranate trees.
وهلق معروفة يعني الرمان، باصوطة مشهورة بكل سوريا.
And now pomegranates are well-known, I mean, Basouta is
famous all over Syria.
وبعد منهم انتشر بكل المنطقة، وهلق كل الناس عم بيزرعوه.
And after them, it spread throughout the entire region, and
now everyone is planting it.
يعني من 100 سنة فقط اجا الرمان على منطقة عفرين؟
So pomegranates only came to the Afrin region 100 years ago?
تقريباً.
Approximately.
من وين؟ ليش؟ من وين اجا على منطقة عفرين وين كان؟
From where? Why? Where did it come from to the Afrin region,
where was it?
والله أنا ما بعرف بالضبط التاريخ اللي بعرفه إنه أول شيء
مثلاً كانوا بيزرعوه بالساحل ما ساحل أو جسر الشغور.
Well, I don't know the exact history. What I do know is
that, for example, they used to plant it first on the coast,
or in Jisr al-Shughur.
بس من وين اجت الشتل لهون على باصوطة، كل الناس أخذوه من بعضهم
وصاروا يستفيدوا منه ويزرعوه.
But where the seedlings came from to Basouta, everyone took
it from each other and started benefiting from it and
planting it.
يعني من 100 سنة الرمان في الباسوطة. وين بعدها انتقل؟ وين أهم
المناطق لزراعة الرمان بعفرين؟
So pomegranates have been in Basouta for 100 years. Where
did it go next? Where are the most important pomegranate-
growing areas in Afrin?
أكثر شيء، أكثر شيء الأراضي اللي صايرة جنب النهر لأنه في مي.
يعني الرمان بتعيش على المي.
The most, the most are the lands right next to the river
because there is water. Pomegranates survive on water.
إذا ما كانت مي متوفرة ما بتعيش شجرة الرمان، لذلك أكثر شيء
انتشر على طرفي نهر عفرين.
If water isn't available, the pomegranate tree won't
survive, so it spread mostly on both sides of the Afrin
River.
آها، كل القرى اللي على طرفي نهر عفرين؟ يعني مثلاً لو رحنا
على الغزاوية في؟
Aha, all the villages on both sides of the Afrin River?
Meaning, for example, if we went to Ghazawiya, is there any?
فيه.
There is.
تل سلور في؟
Tell Salour, is there any?
لـ دير بلوط. برج عبدالو موجودة بغزاوية، اسكان، جلمة..
All the way to Deir Ballout. Burj Abdalo has it, Ghazawiya,
Iskan, Jalma...
لتوصل على حدود تركيا.
All the way to the Turkish border.
أيوا، وحتى هون بعين دارة...
Yes, and even here in Ain Dara...
أكيد في بعين دارة، بترندة، والقرى اللي قدامها كمان يعني قبل
عفرين من سد ميدانكي وأنت جاي على طرفي النهر في شجرة الرمان.
Surely there is in Ain Dara, in Turandah, and the villages
ahead as well, meaning before Afrin, from Midanki Dam as you
come down on both sides of the river, there are pomegranate
trees.
طيب أمشي شوي أبو إدريس هيك. باعتبار في هون أرض خضراء خلينا
نتفرج شوي.
Okay, let's walk a bit, Abu Idris, this way. Since there is
green land here, let's take a look.
هلق شو بيمثل الرمان لأهل الباسوطة؟ شو الرمان بالنسبة لأهل
الباسوطة؟
Now, what does the pomegranate represent for the people of
Basouta? What is the pomegranate to the people of Basouta?
والله الرمان تعتبر رمز باصوطة يعني أكثر الناس يعني بيشتغلوا
بالرمان لأنه هي صايرة مثلاً مصدر معيشتنا.
Well, the pomegranate is considered a symbol of Basouta, I
mean most people work with pomegranates because it has
become, for example, our source of livelihood.
كل رمان اللي بمنطقة عفرين، أهل باصوطة بيروحوا بيضمنوه،
بيجيبوه بيحطوه بالبرادات أو بالصوابير، بيخزنوه وبعدين
بينزلوه على السوق.
All the pomegranates in the Afrin region, the people of
Basouta go and lease them, bring them, and put them in
refrigerators or in piles, store them, and then take them to
the market.
آه، يعني أهل الباسوطة مو بس رمانهم؟
Oh, so it's not just the pomegranates of the people of
Basouta?
لا كل الرمان الموجود بمنطقة عفرين.
No, all the pomegranates in the Afrin region.
بيروحوا بيضمنوه.
They go and lease them.
بيضمنوه أكثر البساتين بيضمنوه بيجيبوه لهون، بيحطوه بالبرادات
وبعدين، أو بالصوابير، وشي شهر شهرين لتخلص هالكمية الزائدة
بالسوق، بعدين بينزلوه على السوق.
They lease most of the orchards, they lease them and bring
them here, put them in refrigerators and then, or in piles,
and for a month or two until this surplus quantity in the
market is gone, then they take it to the market.
وبيصدروه على العراق كمان.
And they export it to Iraq too.
بصدروه رمان ولا بصدروه دبس رمان؟
Do they export it as pomegranates or as pomegranate
molasses?
لا الرمان بيصدروه.
No, they export pomegranates.
أكثر شيء للعراق؟
Mostly to Iraq?
للعراق، إيه.
To Iraq, yes.
وبالتالي هو رمز للحياة، هو النهر...
And therefore, it is a symbol of life, it is the river...
بالضبط هي يعني مصدر الحياة هون بباصوطة، يعني أكثر الناس
بيعتمدوا على زراعة الرمان.
Exactly, it is the source of life here in Basouta, I mean
most people rely on planting pomegranates.
بس بالفترة الأخيرة، يعني للأسف يعني، رخص الأسعار، العالم
تركوا هالصنعة، صاروا يشتغلوا بالفواكه وما فواكه، هلق مثلاً
باصوطة تقريبا أقل شي نصها فيها شجره الرمان.
But recently, meaning unfortunately, the prices dropped,
people left this profession, they started working with
fruits and such, now for example, Basouta, at least half of
it has pomegranate trees.
لاحظت إنه في منغا؟
I noticed there are mangoes?
في منغا وفي كل أنواع الفواكه عنا بباصوطة.
There are mangoes and all kinds of fruits here in Basouta.
بينما الرمان هلق صار الناس يعني خففوا زرعه، أكثر شيء بيقلعوا
الشجر ويزرعوا بدال منه الفواكه.
While with pomegranates, people have started to reduce
planting them, mostly they uproot the trees and plant fruits
instead.
فواكه. شقد عمر شجرة الرمان شقد بتبقى يعني لتثمر؟
Fruits. What is the lifespan of a pomegranate tree, how long
does it take to bear fruit?
تقريباً، إيه تثمر يعني بعد أربع خمس سنوات إذا خدمتها على
المزبوط، بعد خمس سنوات بتثمر، وبتطول شي خمسين سنة.
Approximately, it bears fruit after four or five years if
you take good care of it, after five years it bears fruit,
and it lives for about fifty years.
50 سنة. إيشو المشاكل اللي عم بيعاني منها الرمان؟ زراعة
الرمان؟
50 years. What are the problems that pomegranates suffer
from? Pomegranate farming?
والله يعني اللي بيزرع مي، ماء بس، تأمن له المي، وشوية
المبيدات، وكل شيء يعني الأدوية، سماد، وأكثر شيء وفرة المي.
Well, the one who plants needs water, water only, secure
water for it, and some pesticides, and everything, I mean
medicines, fertilizer, and most importantly the abundance of
water.
وفرة المي. وإن شاء الله متوفرة؟
The abundance of water. And God willing, it's available?
والله هلق العالم عم بيعانوا تعرف غلاء سعر المازوت، والمشاكل
اللي صايرة، يعني العالم الفلاح بيعاني يعني هلق صار بيعانوا
مو مثل الأول.
Well, right now people are suffering, you know the high
price of diesel, and the problems that are happening, I mean
the farmer is suffering, now they are suffering, not like
before.
بس الحمد لله مية النهر عفرين، ومية السد يعني عم توفر النقص.
But thank God, the water of the Afrin River and the dam
water, meaning it makes up for the shortage.
فينا نقول إنه معظم أهالي الباسوطة بيعتمدوا في معيشتهم على
الرمان؟
Can we say that most of the people of Basouta rely on
pomegranates for their livelihood?
تقريباً يعني بدك تعتبر، يعني نصفهم بيعتمدوا على الرمان،
وأكثر شيء ما قلت لك الفواكه، بس الرمان المصدر الأساسي، يعني
الفلاح اللي ما بيشتغل بالرمان معناته هذا فلاح يعني مو أصيل
كسلان.
Approximately, you could consider, I mean half of them rely
on pomegranates, and mostly as I told you fruits, but the
pomegranate is the primary source, I mean a farmer who
doesn't work with pomegranates means this is a farmer who
is, I mean, not authentic, lazy.
الله يرزقكم يا رب. شو هذا؟ هذا شو هذا؟
May God bless you. What is this? What is this?
هذا شوندر.
This is beetroot.
شوندر أحمر؟
Red beetroot?
إيه، شوندر أحمر.
Yes, red beetroot.
وهذا سلق. وهذا شو بيسموه؟
And this is chard. And this, what do they call it?
والله نسيت اسمها.
honestly I forgot its name.
طيب.
Alright.
هذا جبل ليلون؟
Is this Mount Layloun?
إيه جبل ليلون.
Yes, Mount Layloun.
وهاي الغزاوية؟
And is this Ghazawiya?
لا، مو غزاوية، باصوطة عفواً باصوطة. وقلعة الباصوطة.
No, not Ghazawiya, Basouta, sorry Basouta. And the Citadel
of Basouta.
قلعة الباصوطة، تمام.
The Citadel of Basouta, great.
ما شاء الله، الله يحمي هالبلد يا رب. جبل الأحلام.
Mashallah, may God protect this land. Mount Ahlam.
جبل الأحلام.
Mount Ahlam.
خلينا نروح هلق ع البيت لعندك، نشوف أم إدريس تحكي لنا شوي عن
الأكلات اللي يستعمل فيها الرمان ودبس الرمان.
Let's go to your house now, let's see Umm Idris tell us a
little bit about the dishes that use pomegranates and
pomegranate molasses.
تفضلوا، تفضلوا.
Go ahead, please.
(موسيقى)
(Music)
السلام عليكم. أم إدريس شلونك؟
Peace be upon you. Umm Idris, how are you?
الحمد لله، أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم.
Praise be to God, welcome.
الله يعطيك العافية، زوجة المختار.
May God give you health, the Mukhtar's wife.
يا هلا وسهلا فيكم، إيه.
You are very welcome, yes.
شرفي.
Please come in.
أول شيء، خليني ألاحظ شغلة، ما شاء الله بيتكم كتير حلو ويعني
جنة. جنة يا أبو إدريس بيتكم.
First of all, let me point something out, mashallah your
house is very beautiful, and it's like a paradise. Your
house is a paradise, Abu Idris.
تسلم، عيونك الحلوين.
Thank you, your eyes are beautiful.
تسلمي يا أم إدريس. شو قد صار له عمر هالبيت؟
Thank you, Umm Idris. How old is this house?
عمر هالبيت، تقريبا شيء 25 سنة.
This house is about 25 years old.
25 سنة؟ بس ما شاء الله، في تقريبا كل أنواع الفواكه والورود
والزهور.
25 years? But mashallah, there are almost all kinds of
fruits, roses, and flowers.
يا أستاذ، هي شغلتنا، يعني إذا ما زرعنا أهل الباصوطة وما
يزرعوا زرع وشجر، معناته مانا أهل الباصوطة، مانا من باصوطة.
Sir, this is what we do, I mean if we, the people of
Basouta, don't plant crops and trees, then we are not the
people of Basouta, we are not from Basouta.
أكيد. الله يقويكم.
Absolutely. May God give you strength.
تسلم، أهلاً وسهلاً.
Thank you, welcome.
أم إدريس، نحن صورنا جولة بالضيعة، حكينا عن الرمان، موسم
الرمان، أنواع الرمان اللي...
Umm Idris, we filmed a tour of the village, we talked about
pomegranates, the pomegranate season, the types of
pomegranates that...
في الضيعة عمر الرمان وكذا وحكينا عن دبس الرمان.
In the village, the life of pomegranates and such, and we
talked about pomegranate molasses.
بدنا نعرف يعني ايشو هي استعمالات الرمان في الباسوطة؟
We want to know, what are the uses of pomegranates in
Basouta?
شو هي الأكلات اللي بتستعملوها في الرمان أو دبس الرمان؟
What are the dishes in which you use pomegranates or
pomegranate molasses?
الله يعطيكن العافية أول شي.
First of all, may God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health too.
هي دبس الرمان تعتبر أنه مادة أساسي من المونة للبيت.
Pomegranate molasses is considered an essential pantry item
for the house.
يعني الرمان بتعرف أنه أهل باصوطة مشهورين بالرمان وبالدبس
الرمان.
I mean pomegranates, you know the people of Basouta are
famous for pomegranates and pomegranate molasses.
بتستعمل لعدة أكلات.
It's used for several dishes.
يعني منهن الأكلة الرئيسية بيقولوا اللحم عجين، عش البلبل.
Some of them, the main dish, they call it Lahmacun, Osh El
Bulbul.
حشوة الكبة، كبة مقلية.
Kibbeh stuffing, fried Kibbeh.
نعم.
Yes.
مثلاً سلطة جرجير.
For example, arugula salad.
زيتون مثلاً الصبح بكير بتحط فطور هيك صحن زيتون، معلقتين دبس
رمان، يعني بتعطي هيك نكهة كويسة.
Olives, for instance, early in the morning you set a
breakfast with an olive plate, two spoons of pomegranate
molasses, it gives a good flavor.
سفرجلية؟
Safarjalia (quince stew)?
سفرجلية.
Safarjalia.
مثلاً كبة نية، نحن عنا منساوي كبة نية، هي بساووا يعني كم
طريقة، بس الطريقة اللي منساوي نحن.
For example, raw Kibbeh. We make raw Kibbeh. They make it in
a few ways, but the way we make it...
مثلاً منحط كمان دبس الرمان.
For instance, we also add pomegranate molasses to it.
ولسه في يعني، في نسيت أنه كم أكلة لسه في.
And there are still more, I forgot some dishes, there are
still more.
يالانجي.
Yalanji.
إي، بتنحط كمان باليالانجي، ومثلاً إذا أكلت شي أكلة دسمة،
بتحط هيك نص كاسة مثلاً من الهي دبس رمان.
Yes, it is also put in Yalanji. And for example, if you ate
a heavy dish, you put like half a cup of this pomegranate
molasses.
وحط فوقها مي وحليها واشربها مثلاً.
And add water to it, sweeten it, and drink it, for example.
حليها؟
Sweeten it?
إي لكان، مثل العصير بتصير.
Yes of course, it becomes like juice.
يعني بتحط له سكر؟
You mean you add sugar to it?
لا لا، مي مي.
No, no, water, water.
مي، بس مي، مثلاً هالكاسة حطيت إزا لهون دبس الرمان، حط فوقها
مي وحركه واشربه.
Water, just water. For example, in this cup, if you put
pomegranate molasses up to here, add water over it, stir it,
and drink it.
تمام.
Great.
مثلاً مثل كبة، مثل أكلات دسمة، شاوي، ما شاوي، هيك إزا أكلت،
مشان الكوليسترول والشحوم، يعني هيك مفيدة كتير.
For example, like Kibbeh, heavy dishes, grilled meat and
such, if you ate them, it's very useful for cholesterol and
fats.
ما شاء الله، أم إدريس دارسة، دكتورة!
Wow, Um Idris is educated, a doctor!
منعيش بباصوطة وما منعرف يعني بدبس الرمان!
We live in Basouta, how could we not know about pomegranate
molasses!
ما بيصير.
That's not possible.
إزا حكينا عن الباصوطة وعن الإنسان في الباصوطة.
If we talked about Basouta and the people in Basouta.
ملامح وطباع ابن الباصوطة ايشو هي؟ أنا شايف في بداخلكم فرحة
هيك أنه أنتم من الباصوطة.
What are the traits and characteristics of Basouta's people?
I see inside you a joy that you are from Basouta.
ايشو بيعنيلك يعني ابن الباصوطة؟
What does it mean to you to be from Basouta?
والله يا أستاذ أول شي نحن منفتخر بباصوطة لأنه قرية سياحية
ومشهورة وقديمة.
Well sir, first of all, we are proud of Basouta because it
is a famous, old, and touristy village.
وكل الناس كانوا عم يجوا بيزوروها، وناسها طيبين.
And all people used to come and visit it, and its people are
kind.
وأكتر شي يعني نشيطين بيشتغلوا، يعني عمال بيحبوا شغلهم بيحبوا
أرضهم، مرتبطين بأرضهم مرتبطين بـ...
And most importantly, they are active and hardworking,
workers who love their jobs and their land, connected to
their land, connected to...
بضيعتهم، يعني أهل باصوطة إذا طالعهم من باصوطة متل السمكة إذا
طلعتها من المي معناتها بتختنق.
To their village. I mean, the people of Basouta, if you take
them out of Basouta, it's like a fish out of water, it
suffocates.
نحن يعني باصوطة غالية علينا كتير.
For us, Basouta is very precious to us.
يا سيدي الله يديمكم للباصوطة ويديم الباصوطة عليكم، وغنية
بالمياه.
Sir, may God keep you for Basouta and keep Basouta for you,
and it is rich in water.
غنية بالمياه طبعاً أكيد، أكيد، يعني النبعة طبعاً يعني مصدر
الحياة بقلب الباصوطة هي...
Rich in water of course, sure, sure. The spring is
definitely the source of life in the heart of Basouta...
هي النبعة الكبيرة وبتنبع فيها مي تقريباً شي ٣٠ إنش، أكتر من
٣٠ إنش مي.
This large spring, water flows from it, about 30 inches,
more than 30 inches of water.
وبتنسقى كل هالأراضي، وعنا المي الـ... يعني الـ...
And all these lands are irrigated by it. And our water... I
mean...
الأرض وقت بيحفروا بيار، ميتنا كمان مي غميقة، يعني حوالي ٣٠
متر بتطلع المي.
When they dig wells in the land, our water is deep, I mean,
at about 30 meters, water comes out.
وين ما حفرت بير مي بتطلع مي.
Wherever you dig a water well, water will come out.
هلا أعتقد نهر عفرين بيحد القرية، أو بيمر من يعني غرب القرية؟
Now I believe the Afrin River borders the village, or passes
through the west of the village?
إي بيمر من غرب القرية، وتقريباً تلت ربع أراضي الضيعة بينسقى
من مية النهر، بيستفيدوا منها.
Yes, it passes through the west of the village, and almost
three-quarters of the village's lands are irrigated from the
river's water, they benefit from it.
ربع الأراضي.
A quarter of the lands.
والنبعة بتسقي الباقي؟
And the spring irrigates the rest?
تقريباً نفس الشي، إي وفي بيار وهلا من تقريباً ١٥ سنة ٢٠ سنة
جايتنا مية القناة من سد ميدانكي كمان نستفيد منها.
Almost the same, yes, and there are wells. And now, for
about 15 or 20 years, we've had canal water from the Midanki
Dam, we also benefit from it.
ما شاء الله.
Wow.
سؤال، ايشو أنواع الفواكه والخضراوات اللي بتنزرع هون غير
الرمان؟
A question, what types of fruits and vegetables are planted
here other than pomegranates?
حالياً بس، متل ايش مثلاً؟ في موسم ايش؟
Currently, for instance, like what? What season are we in?
هلق عنا المانجا آخر شي موسم المانجا.
Right now, we have mangoes, the mango season is the last.
بس جميع أنواع الفواكه بتنزرع عنا بباصوطة، بتبلش من الشهر
الرابع من موسم الجانرك.
But all types of fruits are planted here in Basouta,
starting from the fourth month with the green plum season.
وبعد منها بتيجي موسم الدراق وخوخ ومشمش وتفاح، وبعدين رمان
لتوصل لشهر الدعش موسم المانجا.
And after that comes the season for peaches, plums,
apricots, and apples, and then pomegranates, until you reach
the eleventh month, the mango season.
يعني ما بتنقطع المواسم عنا بباصوطة.
So the seasons never stop here in Basouta.
ما شاء الله، احكي لي عن المناخ تبعها، هلا نحن يعني تقريباً
الساعة خمسة وشوي الجو كتير لطيف.
Wow. Tell me about its climate. Now it's about a bit past
five, and the weather is very nice.
يا سيدي الجو عنا معتدل يعني الجو متل ما بيقولوا مناسب لكل
شي.
Sir, our weather is moderate, meaning the weather, as they
say, is suitable for everything.
بالصيف في يعني جو معتدل، في كتير بيجوا في ناس عم يجوا
بيصيفوا هون...
In summer, it has a moderate weather, many people come to
spend their summer here...
بباصوطة، سبب وفرة المياه والشجر ما شجر، يعني بيعدل الجو.
In Basouta, due to the abundance of water and trees, it
moderates the weather.
وبالشتي يعني، ما زيادة برد يعني، كمان معتدل يعني بتتحمل
الجو.
And in winter, it's not too cold, it's also moderate, so you
can bear the weather.
نعم، نعم.
Yes, yes.
أم إدريس، هلا متل ما قال أبو إدريس، الباصوطة بلد سياحي.
Um Idris, as Abu Idris said, Basouta is a tourist town.
ويعني كان كتير يجوا ناس من حلب ومن غير حلب، يعني العطل
الصيفية يوم الجمعة، يوم الأحد، يجوا ع نبعة الباصوطة، يجوا
ع... احكي لي عن هي الإيام كيف كانت؟
And a lot of people used to come from Aleppo and outside of
Aleppo, like during the summer holidays on Fridays and
Sundays. They'd come to the Basouta spring, they'd come...
Tell me about those days, how were they?
والله كانت أيام حلوة، يعني هي باصوطة متل ما قال أبو إدريس،
طبيعتها أنه...
Well, they were beautiful days. I mean, Basouta, as Abu
Idris said, its nature is that...
ضيعة سياحية، إي فمن كل أنحاء سوريا كانوا يجوا زوار ويسهروا.
A tourist village, yes. So visitors from all over Syria
would come and stay up late.
يعني بيقعدوا تحت هالشجرات وجنب هالساقية المي، وبيشووا مثلاً
إيش ما بدك بيساووا يعني.
They'd sit under these trees and next to this water stream,
and they'd grill, for instance, they'd do whatever you want.
بيساووا حفلات؟
Would they throw parties?
بيساووا حفلات، إيش ما بدك بيساووا.
They'd throw parties, whatever you want, they'd do.
طيب، حافظانة شي من الأغاني منطقة الباصوطة، عن الباصوطة، شي
تراث الباصوطة؟
Well, have you memorized any songs from the Basouta region,
about Basouta, something from the heritage of Basouta?
أنا وأغاني يعني...
Me and songs are...
فلكلور الباصوطة.
Basouta's folklore.
بعرف لابسة، بس أنا وأغاني يعني، بدك تسامحني يعني.
I know I'm wearing traditional clothes, but me and songs...
you have to excuse me.
طيب، منحول ع أبو إدريس.
Alright, we switch to Abu Idris.
إي والله يا أستاذي والله هي مو اختصاصنا يعني عم ندندن شوي بس
ما منغني.
Yes sir, honestly, this is not our specialty. I mean, we hum
a little, but we don't sing.
طيب دندن شوي.
Alright, hum a little.
في مختصين للغناء.
There are specialists for singing.
في مختصين، يعني هو كل واحد إلو اختصاصه وإلو شغلته، هلا قول
نحن يعني شغل دبس رمان منساوي، شغل البستان منساوي.
There are specialists. Everyone has their specialty and
their job. Like us, say we make pomegranate molasses, we
work in the orchard.
مثلاً الرجال بيروحوا بيكسحوا شجر، منشيل الحطب، منجيبه عالبيت
مثلاً، هيك شغلات منساوي، بس أما الغناء...
For example, the men go prune the trees, we collect the
firewood, and we bring it home for example, we do such
things, but as for singing...
طيب.
Okay.
طيب يعني هلا باعتبار الرمان أنت قلت رمز لأهل الباصوطة من شوي
حكيتلي، هاد الرمز ما دخل في الفلكلور والأغاني والتراث؟
So considering the pomegranate is a symbol for the people of
Basouta as you just told me, didn't this symbol enter the
folklore, songs, and heritage?
والله في، في أغنية مشهورة عالباصوطة، يعني عم بيقولوا
بمعنى...
Actually there is, there's a famous song about Basouta, they
say it meaning...
احكيها بالكردي، إيوا.
Say it in Kurdish, yes.
Çûn Basûtê hinar e, qefik tijî hinar e.
Çûn Basûtê hinar e, qefik tijî hinar e. (They went to
Basouta, it's pomegranates, the basket is full of
pomegranates.)
يعني معناته رحت عالباصوطة وجبت سلة رمان وسلة الرمان صار من
نصيب العروسة وهي، هالحكي هاد.
Which means I went to Basouta and brought a basket of
pomegranates, and the basket of pomegranates became the
bride's share, and such talk.
جميل، حافظانها كلها؟
Beautiful. Do you know it all by heart?
تقريباً.
Almost.
قولنا ياها معلش؟
Can you say it for us, please?
لا دكتور والله أستاذنا، ما بيطلع معي بعدين بشوه الأغنية و...
No, doctor, really, sir, I can't do it, then I'll ruin the
song and...
بس ترجمتها!
But you just translated it!
في إله أصحابها، بعدين بيرفعوا دعوى علينا.
It has its owners, later they will file a lawsuit against
us.
سؤال، عصير الرمان كمان يعني بيتمون متل دبس الرمان؟
A question, is pomegranate juice also stored as a pantry
item like pomegranate molasses?
إي بيتمون إذا في براد، مثلاً في فريزة بيتمون، مثلاً بتحط
بالقناني، بتحط بالفريزة.
Yes, it is stored if there is a fridge. For example, if
there's a freezer, it is stored. Like, you put it in
bottles, and you put them in the freezer.
إيمتى ما بدك، سوي فيها سفرجلية، مثلاً ضيف للضيوف، متل العصير
مثلاً، بيصير.
Whenever you want, you can make Safarjalia with it, for
instance, serve it to guests like juice, it works.
بس أما ما بيطول كتير، إذا ما في براد ما بيطول، إذا في براد
بيطول شهرين تلاتة.
But it doesn't last long, if there's no fridge it doesn't
last, if there is a fridge it lasts two or three months.
يا سيدي الله يعطيكم العافية، نحن انبسطنا كتير والله.
Sir, may God give you health, we enjoyed this a lot, really.
الله يعافيك أستاذ، أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God give you health, sir. Welcome.
حاسين حالنا في بيتنا، وهيدي سوريا البسيطة والطيبة والناس
المتعايشة. إن شاء الله الله بيعيده عليكم وعلينا موسم الرمان
وموسم الزيتون وكل المواسم إن شاء الله بالخير.
We feel like we're in our own home, and this is the simple
and kind Syria, and its coexisting people. God willing, may
God bring back the pomegranate season, the olive season, and
all seasons upon you and us with goodness.
آمين يا رب، آمين يا رب، تسلم.
Amen, O Lord, Amen, O Lord. Thank you.
الله يعطيكم العافية، شكراً أم إدريس.
May God give you health. Thank you, Um Idris.
الله يسلمك يا أهلين وسهلين فيكم.
May God keep you safe. Welcome.
أعزائي المشاهدين، انتهت هالجولة اللي قدمناها إلكن من قرية
الباصوطة بريف مدينة عفرين الجنوبي.
Dear viewers, this tour that we presented to you from the
village of Basouta in the southern countryside of Afrin has
ended.
قدمناها عن موسم الرمان، وحكينا فيها عن دبس الرمان، وأنواع
الرمان، وأيضاً أهم ما يتعلق بالرمان من عادات وتقاليد.
We presented it about the pomegranate season, and we talked
in it about pomegranate molasses, the types of pomegranates,
and also the most important things related to pomegranates
regarding customs and traditions.
سنكون معكم في الأسبوع القادم في جولة جديدة من منطقة سورية
أخرى حبيبة. السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
We will be with you next week on a new tour from another
beloved Syrian region. Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be
upon you.
(Music)